A Finding Aid to the E. P. (Edgar Preston) and Constance Richardson papers, 1814-1996, bulk 1921-1996, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Writings and Notes, 1814-1865, 1931-1983; bulk 1931-1983; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 8.3 Linear feet Boxes 7-15
  - Lectures and Talks, 1934-1982; 4.2; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
    - Ann Arbor, Subjective and Objective in American Painting, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Arkansas Arts Center, What did George Washington Look Like?, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Art Gallery of Hamilton, "American Realists" Exhibition Talk, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Atkins Museum of Fine Arts, George C. Bingham A Hundred Years After, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, The Flowering of a New Society, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Blair County Historical Society Annual Meeting, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Brandeis University, The Sense of Time in 19th Century American Romanticism, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Chicago Symposium, Pioneers of a New Consciousness, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Cincinnati, Travellers in Arcadia, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - City Art Museum of St. Louis, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Clearfield County Historical Society, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - College Art Association, Amateur and Professional in American Painting, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - College Art Association, Attraction of Dogma, Painting and Literature in the 20th Century, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - College Art Association, Collecting in America, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Antiques Forum, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Antiques Forum, Session Two, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Columbus Gallery of Fine Arts, American Romantic Painting, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Corcoran, The Artist in American History, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Delaware Art Museum, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Detroit Art Market, 1938-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Detroit Art Market, Masterpieces of Art, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Detroit Art Market, Standards of Art Criticism, 1940-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Detroit Art Market, Standards of Art Criticism Second Series, 1941-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Detroit Art Market, The Theory of Art Criticism, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Detroit Society of Arts and Crafts Building Dedication, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Franklin Inn, Works of Art, Too, Have Careers and Adventures, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Friends of Independence National Park Art Symposium, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Guatemala, Diego Rivera, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Henry Ford Museum, The American Spirit in Painting, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Indianapolis, American Romantic Painting, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - London, Ontario, Dutch Paintings in the Age of Rembrandt and Frans Hals, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art Lecture Series, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Mount Vernon Ladies' Association of the Union, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - National Collection of Fine Arts Symposium, The Opportunities and Needs for Research in American Art, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - The National Gallery of Canada, The Southern Neighbor, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Northampton, American Romantic Landscape, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Notes and Outlines, 1934-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 41-45)
    - Notes and Outlines, An Analysis of Modern Taste, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Notes and Outlines, Art in the Modern World, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Notes and Outlines, Baroque, Century of Genius, 1943-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Notes and Outlines, Copley and the Rise of American Spirit, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Notes and Outlines, The Dream of Antiquity, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Notes and Outlines, George Caleb Bingham and the Frontier Experience, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Notes and Outlines, Leonardo da Vinci as Artist, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Notes and Outlines, Problems of Contemporary Art, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Notes and Outlines, Realism in American Painting, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Notes and Outlines, Scholarship in Museums, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Notes and Outlines, What is Painting?, 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - The Numismatic and Antiquarian Society of Philadelphia Annual Meeting, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Oakland Museum, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Parke-Bernet Galleries, The Eclectic Collector Series, What Did Washington Look Like, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Penn State University, Philadelphia, Artistic Capital of the Nation, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Pennsbury Manor, Philadelphia Landscape Painting, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Consultants' Remarks, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Gilbert Stuart Exhibition Talk, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Philadelphia Sunday Breakfast Club, "Art and Money, An Irrelevant Connection", 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Princeton, An Endowed Professorship in American Art, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Santa Barbara, Can History and Art be Combined?, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Smithsonian Institution Conference on Museums and Education, The Museum and Education, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Syracuse University, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Talk on George Washington, Given to a Small Private Audience, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 25)
      Includes 1 sound tape reel
    - University Center in Virginia, Visiting Scholars Program, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - University of Delaware, "American Painting 1857-1869" Exhibition Talk, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - University of Rochester, Memorial Art Gallery, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Virginia, Still Life: The Poetry of Objects, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Treasures of American Museums, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - The Voice of America Forum Lectures, The Dual Heritage: Old World and New, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Walters Art Gallery, The European World around 1400, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Washington, Winslow Homer's Contemporaries, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Washington University, Research Opportunities in American Cultural History: Art History, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Wayne University Scholarship Honor Society, The Difference Between Training and Education, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Wilmington Society of Colonial Wars, What did Washington Look Like, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Wilmington Society of the Fine Arts, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Winterthur Museum Lecture Series, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Youth Art Month, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Youth Art Month, Art as an Interpretation of Modern Life, 1934-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Youth Art Month, Development of Modern Art, circa 1930-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Youth Art Month, Museum Taste and its Sources, 1935-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Youth Art Month, Quality of Imagination in Art, 1936-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - Charles Willson Peale files, 1951-1983; 4.3; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 9-11
    Subseries includes correspondence and drafts of various writing projects about Charles Willson Peale, most prominently Richardson's book titled Charles Willson Peale and his World (1983). Files include research materials on Peale and the Peale family, including the Peale Museum, as well as drafts, typescripts, notes, and clippings.
    - Article, Winterthur Portfolio, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - The Barra Foundation, Inc., Grant, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Catalog Duplicates, circa 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Catalog Entries, circa 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - Catalog Essay, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Catalog Essay, Charles Willson Peale and His World, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Catalog Notes, 1975-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Consultants, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, Copeland, Lammot du Pont, 1964-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, Pfister, Harold, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Cox, Beverly Jones, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Details of the Goldsborough Family, Photographs, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Drafts, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Exhibitions, 1977-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Exhibitions, Photographs, 1977-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Gallery Proofs, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Hindle, Brooke, Manuscript, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Josiah, James, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Landscapes, Photographs, circa 1970-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - The Last Phase, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Lecture, Charles Willson Peale Society, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Lecture, Cosmopolitan Club, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Lecture, Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Lecture, Washington College, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Lectures, 1966, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - List of Artworks, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Maryland Historical Society Exhibition, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Maryland to 1776, 1963-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Correspondence, 1975-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Essay, circa 1970-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Exhibition, 1974-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Lists, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Promotion, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Sellers, Charles, circa 1970-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Supplementary Objects, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Miller, Lilian, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Miniatures, Photographs, circa 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Peale, Anna Claypoole, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Peale, Franklin, circa 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Peale, James, 1969-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Peale, James, Landscapes, 1966-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Peale, James, Miniatures, circa 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Peale, James, Washington Miniature, 1962-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Peale, Mary Jane, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Peale, Raphaelle, 1957, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Peale, Rembrandt, 1966-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Peale, Rembrandt, Mr. William Short, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Peale, Rembrandt, Washington, 1973-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - Peale, Rubens, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - Peale, Sarah M., 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - Peale, Titian R., 1977, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Peale Family, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - Peale Family, Attributions of Portrait, 1967-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Peale Girls, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Peale Museum Project, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 42)
    - Peale Museum Sale, circa 1854; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, Keglan's Committee, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - Photograph Orders, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Porter, Charlotte, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - Reference Materials, 1960-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 47)
    - Research Notebook, circa 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Ryan, Regina, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Sellers, Charles, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Status Report and Drafts, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Still Life Notes, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Washington, George, Portrait, 1951, 1974, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Painting in America files, 1946-1982; 4.4; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 11-12
    Includes publishing and printing documentation for Richardson's 1956 book, Painting in America. Materials are comprised of correspondence, publishing agreements, image permissions, and clippings of reviews.
    - Comments, 1956-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Illustrations, Permissions and Correspondence, 1954-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - New Book, Revised Version, 1966-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - New Last Chapter, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Permissions, 1954-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
    - Reissue, 1960-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Reviews, 1956-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Short History of Painting in America, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Third Edition, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 1946-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 18-19)
    - Thomas Y. Crowell Company, Miscellaneous, 1962-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Thomas Y. Crowell Company, Reprinting, 1957-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Washington Allston files, 1814-1865, 1940-1981; bulk 1940-1981; 4.5; Archival Resource Key; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 12-13
    Includes publishing and printing documentation for various writing projects about Washington Allston, most prominently Richardson's 1948 book, Washington Allston: A Study of the Romantic Artist in America. Materials include correspondence, notes, printed material, research material, clippings, and photographs of Allston's artworks.
    - Apollo, Illustrations, 1947-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Apollo, Text, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Artworks, Boston 1808-1811, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Artworks, Boston and Cambridge, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Artworks, Drawings, 1943, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Artworks, Engravings, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Artworks, Juvenilia and London, 1962-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Artworks, London 1811-1818, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Artworks, Paris and Rome 1802-1808, 1958-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Artworks, Photographs and Correspondence, 1952-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Artworks, Reproductions for Book, 1967, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Artworks, Wrongly Attributed to Allston, 1947-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 14-15)
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1958-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Book Reissue, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Catalogs, 1814-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Charleston, S.C., Newspaper Material, 1947, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, General, 1940-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 20-21)
    - Correspondence, H.W.L. Dana, 1942-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, H.W.L. Dana, 1942-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Research, 1946-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Since Publication of Book, 1948-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Lecture, Allston Symposium at Museum of Fine Arts Boston, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Notes, circa 1944-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Portraits of Allston, 1928-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material, The Atlantic Monthly, 1865; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Printed Material, Lectures on Art and Poems by Washington Allston, 1850; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Printed Material, Lectures on the Works and Genius of Washington Allston by William Ware, 1852; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Printed Material, Monaldi: A Tale by Washington Allston, 1856; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material, Publications, 1947-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Research Material, Allston's Documents, 1946-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Research Material, Leonard Janis' and R.H. Dana's Notes on Allston, 1972-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 13-14)
    - Research Material, Miscellaneous, 1841, 1946-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Thesis, "Washington Allston: Biography of an Aesthetic Experience" by Perry F. Hoberg, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 16-18)
    - Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Books, 1943-1982; 4.6; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 14
    Includes correspondence, permissions, and drafts of Richardson's less prominent books and contributions to books including American Romantic Painting, the History of Philadelphia Project, Museums and Education, Sculpture of Marshall Maynard Fredericks, as well as drafts and notes of an untitled manuscript.
    - American Romantic Painting, Correspondence and Permissions, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - History of Philadelphia Project, The Athens of America, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - History of Philadelphia Project, Editorial Committee, 1967-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
    - Museums and Education Chapter, 1962-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Sculpture of Marshall Maynard Fredericks, Notes and Correspondence, 1975-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Sculpture of Marshall Maynard Fredericks, Photocopied Images, 1959-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 9-11)
    - Untitled Manuscript, I. Introduction, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Untitled Manuscript, II. Elegance, Rank and Status, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Untitled Manuscript, III. The Loyalists, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Untitled Manuscript, IV. The Transformation of Man, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Untitled Manuscript, V. The Ocean Highroad, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Untitled Manuscript, VI. The Ocean Highroad II, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Untitled Manuscript, VI. The Ocean Highroad II, William Williams and Benjamin West, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Untitled Manuscript, VII. The Ocean Highroad, Painting in General, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Untitled Manuscript, VIII, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Untitled Manuscript, VIII. The Birth of Political Caricature, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Untitled Manuscript, IX. The Great Bay of Chesapeake, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Untitled Manuscript, X. The Unquestioning Whig, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Untitled Manuscript, XII. The Dream of Antiquity, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Notes, 1931-1982; 4.7; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 14
    These files are miscellaneous handwritten notes and research materials for writing projects. Materials include handwritten notes, pamphlets, and clippings.
    - Architecture, Renaissance and Baroque, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Artists' Market, 1931-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Dutch Guide, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Opus 2, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Study Group, circa 1954-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Various Writings, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 30-31)
  - Diaries, 1938-1980; 4.8; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 14-15
    Included are annotated appointment books and two personal handwritten diaries. The diaries comment on the social and cultural life of Detroit; the authenticity of paintings; Richardson's reflections on contemporary American painting, thoughts about museums, dealers, artists, and art historians (especially Wilhelm R. Valentiner); and travel.